Finding Aid for Paul L. Grigaut Papers 1929-1969
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Paul L. Grigaut Papers 1929-1969
Grigaut, Paul L.
0.7 linear ft.
Art museum curator, professor of history of art at the University of Michigan; correspondence, photographs and slides, printed ephemera, administrative materials and lecture notes.
9983 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Charles H. Sawyer (donor no. 6366 ) and was received at the Bentley Library in 1999.
The collection is open for research.
Paul Leroy Grigaut was born on August 24, 1905, in Paris, France. He studied at the Lycée Henri IV, the Ecole de Louvre, the University of Paris and the University of Chicago. He also studied at the Fogg Museum of Harvard in 1946 and 1947.
From 1927 to 1946, Mr. Grigaut was an instructor and professor of the humanities at the University of New Hampshire. He joined the Detroit Institute of Arts in 1946 as an assistant curator and became the Institute's chief curator in 1955. He also served as acting director for a time in the early 1960s.
Mr. Grigaut left the Detroit Institute of Arts in 1963 to become the associate director of the Virginia Museum of Fine Arts in Richmond. This career move proved to be short-lived, however, as Grigaut grew increasingly unhappy--both with his surroundings and museum administration. He left Richmond in late 1965 and accepted positions as a professor of the history of art and associate director of the University of Michigan's art museum, positions he retained until his sudden death on Tuesday, March 4,1969.
At the time of his death, Mr. Grigaut was widely recognized as one of the world's leading authorities on American and European decorative art, and the correspondence of his colleagues after his death is an impressive index of the esteem in which he was held. One short telegram simply reads, "Grieve for a great scholar and friend."
The Paul Grigaut collection contains correspondence, photographs and slides, printed ephemera, administrative materials and lecture notes. The collection has been arranged into two series: academic affiliations and a topical file.
Subjects:
Grigaut, Paul L.; Art--Michigan.; Detroit Institute of Arts.; Richmond Museum of Fine Arts.; University of Michigan. Museum of Art.; University of Michigan--Faculty.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Grigaut, Paul L.; Detroit Institute of Arts.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Academic Affiliations, 1945-1969
  The Academic Affiliations series (1945-1969; .3 lin. ft.) consists of three subseries: Detroit Institute of Arts (1945-1963), Richmond Museum of Fine Arts (1963-1965) and University of Michigan Museum of Art (1965-1969). The three subseries contain materials related to Grigaut's tenure at these institutions. The Detroit Institute of Arts subseries consists of four folders and contains typed and written correspondence, materials published by the Institute during Grigaut's tenure, memoranda regarding Grigaut's position as acting director and miscellaneous items. The Richmond Museum of Fine Arts subseries consists of four folders and contains typed and written correspondence, memoranda, an annual report and a few miscellaneous items. The University of Michigan Museum of Art subseries consists of three folders and contains memoranda, typed and written correspondence and miscellaneous items.
  - Detroit Institute of Arts, 1945-1963
    - Administrative Materials, 1962-1965 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, December 1955-July 1963 (Box 1)
    - Institute Publications, 1953-1965 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Richmond Museum of Fine Arts, 1963-1965
    - Administrative Materials, 1962-1963 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, August 1963-May 1965, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - University of Michigan Museum of Art, 1965-1969
    - Administrative Materials, October 1964-April 1968 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, July 1965-March 1969 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous, 1965-1969 (Box 1)
- Topical File
  The Topical File series (.4 lin. ft.) contains 12 folders and consists of a variety of materials, including photographs, newspaper articles, obituaries, biographic materials and correspondence regarding Grigaut's death. There are also substantial amounts of materials related to Grigaut's estate, including correspondence, legal documents and inventory lists.
  - Biographic Materials, 1929-1965 (Box 1)
    (Includes photographic portraits and negatives)
  - Correspondence Regarding Grigaut's Death, 1969 (Box 1)
  - Estate Correspondence, 1969-1973, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Estate Inventory, 1969 (Box 1)
    (includes slides)
  - Exhibition Catalogues, 1930-1969 (Box 1)
  - French Silver (Box 1)
  - Lecture Materials1956, 1957, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Newspaper Articles, 1962-1969 (Box 1)
  - Obituaries, 1969 (Box 1)
  - Photographs (Box 1)
  - Publication Materials, 1964 (Box 1)
  - Silversmiths, 1945-1952 (Box 1)